Guide to the Egon Verheyen papers, 1959-2008
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Egon Verheyen papers
1959-2008
C0217
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
3.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
This collection largely documents Egon Verheyen's research and manuscripts through articles, notes and correspondence. It also contains information about his time as a Robinson Professor at George Mason University.
Verheyen, Egon
Biographical Information
Egon Verheyen was born in Germany in 1936. In 1962 he was awarded a degree in Art History with a minor in Classical Archaeology and Historical Studies from the University of Würzburg. He immigrated to the United States of America in 1966. He worked at many universities including the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, Wesleyan University, University of Michigan, Johns Hopkins University, University of Pennsylvania and the University of Virginia until 1987 when he came to work at George Mason University. From 1987 until his retirement in 2008, he was a Clarence J. Robinson Professor of Humanities at George Mason University.
Besides being a professor, he was also an accomplished writer. His first book was Die Minoritenkirche zu Duisburg, Neue Untersuchungen zu ihrer Geschichte (1959). He then went on to write The Paintings in the Studiolo of Isabella d'Este at Mantua (1971) and The Palazzo del Te in Mantua Images of Love and Politics (1977). He also wrote articles and book reviews including a few articles about early architecture in Washington D.C.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection largely documents Egon Verheyen's research and manuscripts through articles, notes and correspondence. It also contains information about his time as a Robinson Professor at George Mason University.
Series 1 contains correspondence with colleagues and friends about different topics that he was working on or hoped to work on. This series also contains correspondence with institutions that he worked at (except George Mason) and who he worked with to get information from for his works. Newspaper articles and some photographs are interwoven with some of the correspondence. The series is arranged alphabetically then by date.
Series 2 is the largest series in this collection, it contains materials relating to the works done by Egon Verheyen throughout his career. Materials include: copies of research, letters to publishers, research requests, drafts of works, notes, newspaper articles, and some of the finished manuscripts. This series also includes advertisements for lectures and his lecture notes. This series is arranged alphabetically then by date.
Series 3 includes materials relating to Egon Verheyen's time working at George Mason University. This includes correspondence with George Mason colleagues, his time as a Robinson Professor, his time on the CAS Council Task Force and on the Logan Award Committee. It also includes evaluations, course descriptions and his CV. This series also includes materials from his retire party and recognition rewards. This series is arranged alphabetically then by date.
Series 4 contains photographs and illustrations that relate to Verheyen's different projects. Many of the photographs are actually copies of works of art. There are some negatives in this series as well as 2 photographs that Verheyen took of the Gerry Monument. This series is arranged alphabetically then by date.
Arrangement
Organized into four series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1967-2000 (Box 1)
Series 2: Publications, 1959-2003 (Boxes 1-7)
Series 3: George Mason University, 1986-2008 (Boxes 7-8)
Series 4: Photographs, 1960s-1990s (Boxes 8-9)
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the Harold J. Morowitz papers and the Vassily Aksyonov papers
Acquisition Information
Donated by Gwen White in 2012.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
George Mason University--Faculty.; George Mason University.
Geographical Names:
Washington (D.C.)
Subjects:
Architecture; College teachers--Virginia--Fairfax.
Document Types:
Negatives.; Photographs.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1967-2000; (1 box)
  Contains correspondence with colleagues and friends about different topics that he was working on or hoped to work on. Also includes correspondence with institutions that he worked at (except George Mason).
  - Badisches Landesmuseum Karlsruhe, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bialostocki, Jan, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Courtlauld Institute of Art, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fries, 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gomrich, Ernst, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Graf, Dieter, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harleman, Kathleen, 1976-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Heckscher, William S. and Roxanne, 1979-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Huse, Robert, 1967-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1972-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Max-Planck-Institut Bibliotheca Hertziana, Rom, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Munich- Bayerische Staatsgemaldesammulungen, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Princeton, NJ Institute for Advanced Study, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Siebenhuner, Herbert, 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Simon, Erika, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stechow, Wolfgang, 1972-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - University of Massachusetts, Amherest, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - University of Michigan, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - University of Virginia, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - von Effra, H.M., 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Various, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series 2: Publications, 1959-2003; (6 boxes)
  Contains materials relating to the works done by Egon Verheyen throughout his career.
  - Article for the Festschrift fur Herbert Siebenhuner, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Art and Literature, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Folder 1 of 2
  - Art and Literature, 1984-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Folder 2 of 2
  - Book Review: Raphael by John Pop-Hennessy and Raphael by Luitpold Dussler, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - A Deposition by Guglielmo della Porta, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Durer's Cities: Nuremberg and Venice, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - An Early Painting By Frans Pourbus the Younger, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Embellishing the Temple of Liberty, 1979-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Embellishing the Temple of Liberty Part 1, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Embellishing the Temple of Liberty Part 2, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Embellishing the Temple of Liberty (Index and Bibliography), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Emblematica Vol. 1, No. 1. Spring, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Festschrift Jan Bialostocki, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Frazees' Gerry Monument, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Grundfagen der Kunstwissenschaft", 1971-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Heckcher Festschrift (The Verbal and the Visible), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Henry III, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - James Hoban's Design for the White House, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - John Trumbull and the U.S. Capitol, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - John Quincy Adams Project, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Karlsruhe/Petersburg, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Laurence Hall Fowler Exhibit, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lectures, 1959-2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lectures, 1959-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - MacMillan Encyclopedia of Architects, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Music of the 19th Century Harris Theatre, GMU, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - On Devices, Emblems and Architecture, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Paintings in the "Studiolo" of Isabella d'Este at Mantua, 1969-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Palazzo Del Te: In Defense of Jacopo Strada, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Palazzo Del Te In Mantua, 1971-1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Palazzo Del Te In Mantua, 1977-1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Research on Hieroglyphs, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Retaining the Original", 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Rhine Lecture Research, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Sala di Psiche, 1971-1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sculpture in the Federal City: The Tripoli Monument and the Hall of Representatives, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Theodor Fontane Research, 1993-2001 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Theodor Fontane Research, 1993-2001 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Thomas Jefferson European Travels, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Folder 1 of 3
  - Thomas Jefferson European Travels, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Folder 2 of 3
  - Thomas Jefferson European Travels, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Folder 3 of 3
  - Thomas Jefferson Research, 1992-2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Folder 1 of 5
  - Thomas Jefferson Research, 1992-2001 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Folder 2 of 5
  - Thomas Jefferson Research, 1992-2001 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Folder 3 of 5
  - Thomas Jefferson Research, 1992-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Folder 4 of 5
  - Thomas Jefferson Research, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Folder 5 of 5
  - U.S. Capitol, 1990s (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - The Washington Monument 1783-1801, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series 3: George Mason University, 1986-2008; (1 box)
  Contains materials relating to Egon Verheyen's time as a Robinson Professor at George Mason University.
  - CAS Council Task Force, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Course/Teaching Recommendations, 2002-2007 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Dept. of History and Art History, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Egon Verheyen CV, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - GMU, 1986-1993 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - GMU, 1994-2002 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - GMU, 2003-2008 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Logan Award: Ellen Layman, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Logan Award: Gwendolyn White, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Logan Award: Jessica Legnini, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Logan Award: Jessica Legnini, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Peter Stearns/Dave Rossell, 2002-2006 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Robinsons Committees, Task Force, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series 4: Photographs, 1960s-1990s; (1.5 boxes)
  Contains photographs and illustrations that relate to Verheyen's different projects.
  - Gerry Monument, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Illustration Copies, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Illustration Copies, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - L.P. from Illustrirte Zeitung, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Negatives, 1976-1981 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Thomas Jefferson European Travels, 1990s (Box 9, Folder 5)